Niels Nyholt

Curriculum Vitae

Kystvejen 49, 5th floor
DK-8000 Aarhus C
☎ +45 2082 2240
☑ nielsnyholt@gmail.com
 nnyholt.github.io

Research Interests

My primary research interest is in understanding how people's experiences with politics and politicians in their local area shape their political behavior. This has led me to study areas such as electoral accountability in the context of school and hospital closures, nimbyism, the attitudes of residents of disadvantaged neighborhoods, rural resentment, and candidate choice. I like to use experiments or geospatial data to look at questions from a new angle.

Academic positions

2022 - Postdoc, Aarhus University.

Education

- 2022 Ph.D. in Political Science, Aarhus University.Committee: Katherine J. Cramer, Peter Thisted Dinesen & Martin Vinæs Larsen (Chair)
- 2018 **MSc in Political Science**, *University of Copenhagen*.
 with a specialization in Political Behavior and Advanced Quantitative Methods
 Awarded: Centre for Voting and Parties (CVAPs) Thesis Prize 2018
- 2016 **BSc in Political Science**, *University of Copenhagen*.

Other Academic Activities

- 2021 Visiting Researcher, University of Pennsylvania
- 2016 Visiting Student, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

Publications

- 2024 **Nyholt, Niels, Kjær, Ulrik & Hansen, Kasper Møller**, *Kampen om land og by*, in Partiledernes kamp om midten Folketingsvalget 2022, red. Kasper Møller Hansen & Rune Stubager.
- 2024 **Nyholt, Niels**, *Why Do Voters Prefer Local Candidates? Evidence from a Danish Conjoint Survey Experiment*, Political Behavior.
- 2023 **Nyholt, Niels**, *Left behind: Voters' reactions to local school and hospital closures*, European Journal of Political Research.
- 2023 **Nyholt, Niels**, *Politisk adfærd langt fra Slotsholmen*, Samfundsøkonomen.

Working Papers

- n.d. **Larsen, Martin Vinæs, & Nyholt, Niels**, *Understanding Opposition to Apartment Build-ings*, Invited contribution to special issue on Politics of Housing in Journal of Political Institutions and Political Economy.
- n.d. Larsen, Martin Vinæs, & Nyholt, Niels, Understanding Nimbyism: Beyond Home Values and Exclusionary Attitudes, Working paper. Presented at APSA, September 2023 & DPSA 2023..
- n.d. **Finseraas, Henning, Nyholt, Niels, Sohlberg, Jacob, & Sønderskov, Kim Mannemar**, What Determines Opposition to Anti-Religious Speech? Experimental Evidence from Disadvantaged Neighborhoods in the Nordics?.
- n.d. **Finseraas, Henning, Nyholt, Niels, & Sønderskov, Kim Mannemar**, *What Explains the Integration Paradox?*.
- n.d. **Nyholt, Niels**, *Getting Your Fair Share: People's Reaction To Changes In Local Political Priorities*, Working paper. Presented at the Political Behavior Workshop at Aarhus University, February 24 2022 & DPSA 2022..

Teaching and supervising

- 2023, 2024 **Research methods II**, *Aarhus University*, BA course taught in Danish with an externally censored oral exam.
- 2021, 2023 **Political Geography**, *Aarhus University*, MA course taught in Danish with an externally censored written exam. Online in 2021, and co-taught with Kim Mannemar Sønderskov in 2023.
- 2021, 2023 **General Political Science**, *Aarhus University*, BA course taught in Danish with an internally censored written exam.

Service

Reviewer for: Journal of Politics, European Journal of Political Research, Political Behavior, Electoral Studies

Paper presentations at conferences

- 2023 DPSA Annual Meeting, Nyborg, Denmark.
- 2023 APSA Annual Meeting, Los Angeles, US.
- 2022 DPSA Annual Meeting, Nyborg, Denmark.
- 2022 SPSA Annual Meeting, San Antonio, US.
- 2021 APSA Annual Meeting, Seattle, US.

Public outreach

- 2023 LSE EUROPP Blog: How school and hospital closures affect political support
- 2022 TV2 Øst: Se kortet her bor kandidaterne til folketingsvalget

Work Experience

2018 – 2019 **Officer**, *Ministry of Children and Social Affairs*.

Ministerial coordinator for the development of Tilbudsportalen.dk, an IT portal providing municipalities with information on social services and foster homes. Tasks included coordinating with stakeholders, reviewing legislation, and assisting the minister.

2015 - 2017 Student Assistant, Trap Danmark.

Collected and processed statistical material for the 6th edition of Trap Danmark, an encyclopedic work describing Denmark municipality by municipality.

written and spoken

written and spoken

Languages

Danish mother tongue

English proficient

German some knowledge

Skills

Advanced MS-Office, LATEX, R, QGIS

Basic Python, Stata

References

Available on request.